[SPEAKER_00] In the previous session, we went over a very, very important concept, which is the concept of mausuf and sifah, right, the adjective and the noun. So, did everybody understand this concept? Please raise your hand if you did not understand this concept. Okay, alhamdulillah. So you understand. And who remembers the four things that the mausuf and the sifah have to correlate in? Okay. And number four? Forgot the fourth one? Huh? Last harakah, right? In the last harakah, they have to be the same, right? So this is how you know if two things are mausuf and sifah, right? Now, I asked you guys to bring examples from the Qur'an for mausuf and sifah. Was anybody able to bring some examples? Okay, good.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay, good. Very good. This is in Surah Hud. No, sorry, Shura, you're right, yes. Okay, good. So, this means something which is wide, right? Like, that's the literal meaning of it, but it means like, you know, when evil comes to him, you know, when good comes to him and he's so arrogant and he thinks it's all because of his own, you know, his own power, his own might, his own abilities, but when some evil comes to him, all of a sudden he becomes so humble, he's making so much, such wide dua, such vast dua, meaning he's, he's like engrossed in his dua. So, this is describing the dua, dua in adil, right? So, good, mashallah. That's a good example. Yeah, I was reading it,
[SPEAKER_00] not looking for, but it came to me, I think it is, but I, you can check that. This is from Surah Al-Hadith. Very good. So, which word is it specifically? This is the noble reward. Good. There's two actually in that, that ayah. One is, as you said, right? So, let's test it out in the four things. Are they both the same gender? Come on, everybody. Everybody, I want everybody to pay attention. Are they both the same gender? Okay. They're both what? Male or female? Male. Okay. Are they both the same? Same harakah at the end? Yes. Yes. Are they both singular? Yes. They're both singular. And lastly, are they both ma'arifa or nakira? Yes. Which one are they? Both nakira. Both of them are indefinite.
[SPEAKER_00] So, they fit all four things. Therefore, this is ma'usuf and sifah. So, ajr means reward. Kareem means noble, right? Or honorable. So, how would you translate this? Noble reward. All right. Good, mashallah. Before that, you said, Right? Yes. The same ayah. Yeah, mashallah. Very good. This is in Surah Hadid, right? Right? I mean, in Urdu, they just say, But in Arabic, it's Right? Right? So, both of them are male. Both of them have fatha at the end. Right? Both of them are nakira indefinite. And both of them are
[SPEAKER_00] singular. Right? So, it fits all four things. So, qardan means a loan. Right? And hasan means good. Right? So, a good loan. Right? Simple. Right? Good, mashallah. Another example. Ayat bayinat. Good. وَلَقَدْ أَنزَلْنَا إِلَيْكَ آيَاتٍ بَيِّنَاتٍ وَلَقَدْ أَنزَلْنَا إِلَيْكَ آيَاتٍ بَيِّنَاتٍ وَلَقَدْ أَنزَلْنَا إِلَيْكَ آيَاتٍ بَيِّنَاتٍ Right? So, they're both female. They're both plural. Right? Ayat bayinat. Right? I mean, we didn't learn that yet, but we'll learn it inshallah. They're both plural. They both have the same harakah. And they're both nakira. They're both indefinite. So, therefore, they are mausuf and sifah. Right? It means clear signs. Ayat. Ayat is a plural of ayah. Ayah. Ayah. Ayah means signs. And bayinat is a plural of bayin,
[SPEAKER_00] which means clear. So, this would mean clear signs. Everybody understand that? Yeah. Good, mashallah. More examples? وَكَوَاعِبَ أَتْرَابَ Very good, mashallah. وَكَوَاعِبَ أَتْرَابَ That's a lot of brothers' favorite ayah, mashallah. Surat al-Nabaa. Yeah, Surat al-Nabaa. Does anybody know what this ayah means? No, I don't know. Anybody? If anybody was here, if they were here with us on New Year's Eve in our program, then they would know what it means. I'll do the cup, maybe. Cup? I don't want to say anything. Okay. Okay. There's still some brothers in the masjid. Maybe I'll tell them later. Okay, basically, it's talking about the huwur of Jannah. Right? So, kawa'ib means full-breasted women. Right? Talking about the women of Jannah. And, atraban means that, that they are the same age. Right?
[SPEAKER_00] So, that's what the ayah means. So, it is an example of mausuf. I'm not going to write it, though, because there's an exception in there, and I don't want you guys to get confused. But, it's a good example, though. It was you, right? Good example. Okay. Next. That's mudhaf ilayh. See? So, let's just write it down so you know why it's not mausuf and sifah. So, there's a couple of things. Okay, let's say, you guys actually tell me why. Why this is not mausuf and sifah. Okay? Why is this? Or, let's just test it out. Okay, the four things. Are they the same in their gender? No. Jannahat is female. It's a plural of jannah. It has a tamar buta. Naim is male. So, already we have, it doesn't work, right? But, let's keep going. Then, are they both ma'rifah? Are they both definite?
[SPEAKER_00] No. Right? Rather, this is a mudhaf and mudhaf ilayh. You get it? All right. It's good, though. Again, there's no problem if you don't bring a correct example because that's how we learn. That's the whole point of me asking you guys to bring these examples because you're going to bring some that may not be correct. And, that's how we learn how to identify them with accuracy. Okay. So, can you explain? I'm very confused now. Now, the number four rule. So, definite, indefinite, that's what we talked about last time, right? Mm-hmm. So, number one has to be there, right? In order for this to qualify. Sorry? What has to be there? One rule, meaning... No, all four have to be there. No, no. I mean number four. So, there has to be definite or indefinite? Yeah. Meaning both of them have to be either definite or both of them have to be indefinite. Okay. So, how do I... So, again, can you just explain? How would I tell with me, let's say, ayat in
[SPEAKER_00] Balminaat? So, generally, I mean, it's simple, right? If it has a tanween, the general rule is going to be indefinite. And, if it has al, it's going to be definite. So, that's the simplest way to figure out what's definite or indefinite. The only exception is... Proper nouns. Proper nouns. What is a proper noun? A proper noun is a name of somebody or something. So, that will be... Definite, even if it has tanween on it. Right? Because it's a name, it's a specific person. So, you're talking about a definite, a specific person. You get it? Other than that, the general rule to differentiate is if it has al, it's definite. And, if it has tanween on it, it's indefinite. Got it? One more is... Sorry? Yeah. That's a good example, but I'm not going to write it because there is an exception there. And, I'm not going to... I don't want to confuse people, but it's a good example. Good? Can you ask me ayaah for Surah Al-Majallab? Qaradaan hasanan. Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] In duqridu Allah qaradaan hasanan, yuda'ifu lakum... No, no. Yeah, that's it. In duqridu Allah qaradaan hasanan, yuda'ifu... So, same example as this. Qaradaan hasanan. Good. Qaradaan al-jurus. Surah As-Sashlar. No, that's Muda'atun Allah fi-Layh. Actually, no, you're right. Never mind, you're right. But, that's an exception, so I don't want to go into that. It's going to get confusing. Good. Nazirun mubeen. Okay. Nazir means warner. Okay? Mubeen means clear. You got it? Mubeen means clear. So, are they mausuf and sifah? Let's see. They both are male, right? They both are singular.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay? They both have dhamma as their anharaka, and they're both indefinite. So, therefore, they are mausuf and sifah. Okay? And, nazir means warner. Mubeen means clear. So, how would you translate this? A clear warner. Good, mashallah. Good example. Dhalika huwa alfadlu alkabeer. Yeah. That's in Surah... It's in the 25th Juz. In Surah... The one before... I'm forgetting the Surah name. Come on, Hufa. No, after Surah Shura. I think it's in there. Or, it might be in Shura, actually. Lahumma yasha'una inda rabbim. Dhalika huwa alfadlu alkabeer. Dhalika alladhi yubashiru Allah wa ibadahu alladhi ina aman wa amin saliha. That's in Surah Shura. Okay. Al-fadlu alkabeer. Good example, mashallah.
[SPEAKER_00] Come on, Hufa. Daraweeh is coming very soon. Al-fadlu alkabeeru. Right? I mean, I think it comes multiple times, but usually it's without al. It's like, wabashiril mu'mina bi anna lahum min Allahi fadlan. Al-fadlu alkabeeru. It only comes once. Dhalika huwa alfadlu alkabeeru. That's all I remember. If you remember another place, you can tell me. Okay. So, let's just go over this. Right? So, they're both male. They're both singular. They both have al. So, they're both definite. And they both have dhamma. So, therefore, it's mausuf and sifah. And how would you translate it? Fadl means grace. Right? And kabeer means great. Right? So, a great grace. Okay. You were raising it, right? Very good. Yeah. Wal yawm al-akhiri. Right? Very good example.
[SPEAKER_00] Because it comes very often. Okay. Okay. Al-yawm al-akhiri. Okay, look. So, al-akhir. So, okay. First of all, they're both, ma'arifa, they're both definite. Because they both have al. Right? They're both male. They both have kasra. And they both, what was the fourth thing? They're both singular. Right? Now, al-yawm means day. Al-akhir means last. So, how would you translate this? The last day. Okay? So, whenever you say now, al-yawm al-akhir, in kuntum tu'minu billahi wal-yawm al-akhiri, then, you know that it means the last day. And you know why it means that. Have we got it? Another example I can think of is, al-amalu salih. Right? ilayhi yas'adu al-karimu al-tayyibu wal-amalu salihu yarfau. That's
[SPEAKER_00] in Surah Fathir, I think. Right? Yes or no? Or Fath? Anybody? Okay. Okay. Okay, let's see what this means. Al-amalu salihu. Okay? Okay, they're both male, right? They both have al, they're both definite, they're both singular, and they both have dhamma. So, they fit all four things. And al-amal means action, and salih means good. So, how would you translate that? Good action. Everybody got it? Isn't there another one in the ayah? Al-karimu al-tayyibu? Very good, yeah. ilayhi yas'adu al-karimu al-tayyibu.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay, al-karimu al-tayyibu, right? Al-karim is like the singular of kalim, like it's a word, right? Al-tayyib means pure, right? So, al-karim, it's singular. This is also singular. It's male. This is also male. It's both. Dhamma, this is also dhamma. And this is definite, and this is also definite, al, right? Therefore, they are mawsuf and sifah, right? Al-kalim means word. Al-tayyib means pure. How would you translate it? Pure word. Pure word, good. This is an interesting one. Wa-kasim min mayin. So, a flowing stream, but there is from a flowing stream. Yeah, so that's different. Because it has min. Yeah, min. There shouldn't be anything between, yeah. Good. But that's a little bit of an exception because I don't want to confuse people. But if you look at Dhankar, it doesn't have a
[SPEAKER_00] taam or buta, right? So, but it's a good example. Okay. So, it's talking about Dhul-Qarnayn, and Dhul-Qarnayn, and Jujah, and Jujah, and Mufsidun, and Al-Kahf. Okay. But I don't think there's a Mufsidun over there. No, there's not. I don't think there's a Mufsidun over there. You knew there was a proper noun. There was a name like someone in particular. No, but it's just a name. It's just two names. Yeah, Juj. Wa-Ma-Juj. They're two names of different groups. Yeah. Good. Very good. Good. Kam min fi'atin qaleelatin? That's a good example, because you can see how the harakah follows along.
[SPEAKER_00] So, the ayah is, Kam min fi'atin? Sorry. Qaleelatin qaleelatin ghalabat fi'atan kathiratan. Right? So, fi'a. Okay, this is singular. This is singular. This is female. This is female. This is indefinite. This is indefinite. This is kasrat. This is kasrat. So, therefore, they are mausuf and sifah. Right? I'm not repeating this over and over again to show you guys to be bored. Like, so that you can drill it in. So, I want you guys to start thinking systematically like this. Right? When you're reading in the Quran, you're like, okay, you see this and this? Okay. They fit this. They fit this. They fit this. Okay, that's it. That's how your mind has to work with process of elimination. Right? Otherwise, these rules are just going to be theoretical rules and you're never going to be able to implement them. So, you have to start training your mind to think like this. As soon as you see two words like this, they
[SPEAKER_00] seem like they match, but you have to put them to the test. Put them to these four filters. Once they pass these four filters, then you can confidently say that this is mausuf and sifah and you can translate them accordingly. Everybody understand that? Okay, that's why I'm bringing so many different examples. I want it to really be drilled down because this is one of the most common, uh, things that come up in Arabic language. So, if you can grasp this, it will grasp a huge portion. Just like mudawaf, mudawaf filay, this is another major rule that comes very often. Okay. So, they match in all four things. So, fi'ah means jama'ah, means a group. And qalila means small, right? Or little, but in this case, you would translate it as small, right? And this is the same thing, fi'ah, right? Fi'atan kathiratan, right? A large group, right? So, the ayah is, كم من فئة قليلة غلبت فئة كثيرة بإذن الله That how many small groups are there that overcome a large group by the help of Allah, by the permission of Allah subhanahu wa ta'ala.
[SPEAKER_00] Everybody got it? So, and you see how, again, that the harakah of the sifah, the adjective automatically follows the harakah of the mausuf, the thing that's being described. Everybody understand that? So, this is a good example that shows, brings that out and makes it clear, right? By the way, we can, I think we can add this to another family, right? This mausuf and sifah, right? So, this would be the followers, the followers. They're not leaders, they just follow others, right? So, this family, in Arabic, it's called at-tawabe' At-tawabe' At-tawabe' The followers, right? So, what they do is they just follow the harakah of whatever comes right before them. Right? So, mausuf and sifah are part of this family.
[SPEAKER_00] Meaning the sifah, sorry. The sifah is part of this family. Because, I mean, mausuf is the thing that's being followed, right? So, we wouldn't consider it part of the family. Okay? So, that's just a side note. Okay, any more example? Or should we start, continue with the lesson? Sorry. Aliyyan kabira, good. Yeah, many of the sifat, the qualities of Allah that are mentioned at the end of ayat are like that. They mention two sifahs together. So, they're describing each other. That's good. Or, but another way to look at it is that they're both khabar, right? They're both, because if you think about it, it's not necessarily mausuf and sifah because they're both khabar. So, aliyyan and kabiran, they're both describing Allah individually, right? It's not like kabiran is describing aliyyan. Do you understand what I mean? So, it's better to say that they're both separate predicates describing Allah
[SPEAKER_00] subhanahu wa ta'ala. So, that wouldn't fully work in this case. But, I understand why you would think that that would be mausuf and sifah. Yeah, I mean, like when it talks about punishment, the adhab and adhim, the adhab and sifah. Good, very good. Perfect, beautiful. So many examples like that, right? Adhabun adhim, adhabun alim, right? Alim, right? Adhabun alimun, adhimun, shadeedun. Any other description of adhab? Adhab al-nukra. Very good. Adhab al-nukra. Ghalif. Good, ghalif. Adhab al-muqim. Very good. Muqim. So many different adjectives of one word of adhab. May Allah protect us from this adhab. Ameen. Okay. Muqim, right? So, in so many different ayahs, right?
[SPEAKER_00] Allah says, وَلَهُمْ عَذَابٌ أَلِيمٌ Right? Or like, yeah, so, adhab is singular. Singular, singular, singular, singular, singular, singular, right? Male, these are all male, right? This is dhamma in this case. These are all dhamma, except in this case, it comes as adhaban. Nukra, right? So, that's there. And over here, it says, وَنَجَّيْنَاهُمْ مِنْ عَذَابٍ غَلِيظٍ Right? That's in, I think, surah Hud, right? Yeah. وَتِلْكَ عَادٌ جَحَدُوا بِأَيَا So, surah Hud. So, in this case, it would be kasra, right? وَلَهُمْ عَذَابٌ مُقِيمٌ That's in surah Ma'idah, right? وَالسَّارِيقُ وَالسَّارِيقَةُ It was after that, right? So, all these cases, these are all sifas of adhab, right? These are all different descriptions. أَلِيم means painful. عَظِيم means great. شَدِيد means severe. نُكْرًا Huh? Terrible. Yeah, same. Terrible, evil. غَلِيظ also means like very... Sorry?
[SPEAKER_00] Thirty? Thirty? Harsh. No, harsh is a good word, yeah. Harsh. Harsh is a good word. مُقِيم means everlasting, right? So, yeah. So, all of these are sifas. مَوْصُوف and صِفَة. Everybody got that? So, every time that comes in the Qur'an, then you know that's a مَوْصُوف and صِفَة. Everybody got that? Does everybody feel like they understand the concept now? Yes. Yes? I'm sorry, what does مُقِيم mean? مُقِيم means everlasting. Yeah. Okay. Is this غَلِيظ a mean order? Is this is close to that word? غَلِيظ Possible. A green bird. No, it's different. It's different. Yeah. I mean, in Arabic, sometimes it is used for that same meaning, but not over here. That's not the meaning it's used over here. Okay. So, hopefully, now this concept is drilled into our minds, inshallah. But I still want, because
[SPEAKER_00] it's clear that all of you didn't do the homework, because only a few people were suggesting ayat. So, I still want those who did not answer, and I will start picking on you guys, whoever didn't say anything today, those who did not bring any examples, I will listen to examples from the next class, inshallah. Okay? So, please be ready, those who did not. I'm looking at all of you who did not say anything this class. Please come ready with examples next class, inshallah. I will not let you guys go anymore. Nobody, there's no more just gliding along with the class. Now, everybody has to be part of the class now. Okay, inshallah? All right? All right. Um. What page were we on? 47. Okay, we were towards the middle of the page, right? Let's just start from the beginning quickly, because now we understood the main important concept over here. Okay.
[SPEAKER_00] All right. Who wants to read? Somebody? Osman, go ahead. Just start from the beginning. Okay, just a side note. Even now we know, the chapter headings, الدرس التاسعو, that's also موصوف and صفة, right? الدرس means lesson, التاسع means ninth, right? So, it's describing the lesson, and they're both male, they're both singular, they're both معرفة, and they're both ضمّة, right? So, it's موصوف and صفة, the ninth lesson. Everybody understand that? Yeah, موصوف always comes first. Yeah, موصوف always comes first, yes. Always comes first. Okay. من هذا رجل من هذا رجل Yeah. Who is this man? Who is this man? Okay. من هذا رجل هو عباس He is عباس Okay. عباس تاجر عباس تاجر Okay, good. عباس
[SPEAKER_00] Read loud and clear, and every single حركة should be clear. عباس تاجر Okay. عباس is a merchant Yeah. عباس تاجر عباس تاجر غنيون عباس تاجر غنيون عباس is a rich merchant. عباس is a rich merchant. Rich merchant, good. So, now we have our first example in the book of موصوف and صفة. We see how they're matching. Tell me, Uthman, how they're matching in all four things. تاجر and غنيون both have the same last haraqas. Okay. They're both indefinite, and they're both male, and what was the last one? And male. Yeah, they're both singular. Good. Mashallah. Very good. Good. I want everybody to, every time I ask you, I want you to be able to list it like that, right? You shouldn't have to look in your notes anymore. You should have it on top of your head. Okay. Continue. حامد مدبس جديد Okay. حامد مدبس جديد حامد is a new teacher.
[SPEAKER_00] Good. Tamim, how, name, tell me how these two are موصوف and صفة. Did they pass the four filters? Yeah, because it's the same. Ending in the haraqas. Okay. Or, I want to say what this is definite or indefinite. Both are definite, right? Teacher and jadeethan. But why? How do you determine whether something is definite or indefinite? Definite is defined, indefinite is not defined. No, but how? I mentioned it earlier in class today. I think because it's حامد. No, it's not. It's just simple. You don't have to think. Yeah, it's just like a person. No, no, no. Either it's, if it's أل, then it's definite. If it's تنوين, it's indefinite. Unless it's a proper noun, then that's a different story. So this would be indefinite, right? Yeah, that's it. Yeah. So they're both indefinite. Okay, good. They're both male. Okay, then? Then they're both, yeah,
[SPEAKER_00] they're both male. All the same haraqas. Both are indefinite. And then... Last one? What is the last one again? Yeah, yeah. I was saying... I mentioned gender or not? You mentioned gender already. There's one more left. Indefinite. I'm not trying to look at my notes. What's the quote? Singular. Oh. Yeah. I didn't mention this? I don't think so. Oh, okay. Yeah. They're both singular. Good. Good. Mashallah. All right. Continue with one. What is this? What is this? This is food. This is... No? No. Okay. What is faqihatun? Faqihatun means fruit. Okay. Let's see. What should I pick on? I see a lot of people avoiding eye contact. It's not gonna work. Brother
[SPEAKER_00] Ali, tell me, are these two mausoof and sifah or not? And do they go through the four filters or not? They're... They're not. Because they're feminine. It's okay. I mean, we're not feminists here. I mean, we're not... We're not misogynistic over here. We don't mind feminine. Okay. They're singular. Feminine. Same ending. Okay. Good. Harakah. Harakah. And the same harakah. And one more thing. And they're... They're indefinite, right? Indefinite. Indefinite. Indefinite. Why are they indefinite? Mafia. No, please. Let the brothers... Because... Oh, because the... No. But in general, how do you tell if something is definite or indefinite?
[SPEAKER_00] The Allah at the beginning, right? No. That's separate. Pretend that doesn't exist. Okay. You're only looking at faqihatun nadidah on its own. Okay. So, you tell me if... Is it definite or indefinite? This would be... I would say it's indefinite. Yeah. Because it's tanween. Yeah. So, tanween generally is indefinite. So, good. So, it matches in all four of these things. All right? So, therefore, this is musuf and sifah. How would you translate it? Faqihat means fruit. Fruit. Tasty fruit. Good. Tasty fruit. Very good. Mashallah. All right. Continue, Rahman. Do you understand me? Yeah. What is that? . What is that? . What is that? What is the type of bird? I forgot the exact... Sparrow. Sparrow. Sparrow. Sparrow. . Okay. Don't translate. Don't translate this. Okay. . Let's see. . Tell me. Are these... Is this musuf and sifah?
[SPEAKER_00] . Yeah. Okay. Does it go through the four filters? . Yeah. . Okay. Good. They're both male. Single. Single. Good. Both singular. Same ending. Same ending. Good. . Yeah. Indefinite. They're both indefinite because they both have tanween. Perfect. Mashallah. All right. So translate it now. Translate it. . . means bird. . Good. The sparrow is a small bird. Very good. Mashallah. All right. . Okay. All right. Who should I pick on now? . Let's see. . Go ahead. . . But I want you to go to the four...
[SPEAKER_00] . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Good, they both have . Good, they're both... . Same Arabic at the end? . . . They're both mo'annah. They're both female. Good. . Good. Both singular and lasting? . very good. Mashallah. Mashallah. They're both indefinite. Mashallah. Very good. Al Hamdulillah. Okay? Okay, so this is مصوف and صفة. لغة means language. I don't think I mentioned that, right? لغة means language. We should know that by now because the name of the book is درس اللغة العربية, right? So اللغة means language. اللغة العربية means language, the language of Arabic, right? The Arabic language, sorry, if you want to be more accurate in translation. What about سهلة? سهلة means easy.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah, that's a new word, sorry. Sorry. سهلة means easy. So إسم البيت أهل وسهلة, is that the same word? Yeah, it's the same word, yeah. Good. العربية اللغة سهلة. Does anybody agree with the statement? العربية اللغة سهلة. Do you agree with the statement? No. No? Why not? I thought it was pretty easy. This is definitely. Okay. All right. I think everybody will agree with this next sentence. So read the next sentence. Okay, good. العربية اللغة جميلة. How about زيشان? Arabic is a beautiful language. Okay, so لغة جميلة. Bring me through the four steps, the four filters. They're both feminine. Good. They're both feminine. And in تنوين. Good.
[SPEAKER_00] They're both تنوين, so they're both indefinite. They are both gender ending and indefinite. Yeah. Ending, yeah. So ending. You said that the last حركة is the same. Good. They're both ضم. And they're both singular. That's it. You got it. That's four. Okay. Good. So then you translate. جميلة means beautiful. So you translate it as? Beautiful. Arabic is a beautiful language. Beautiful language. Okay. Everybody agree with that statement? Yes? Yes. All right. Good. If you didn't agree, I would kick you out of class. Okay. Next. Continue reading. Okay. عمار. Okay. مُجْتَهِدٌ means hardworking. And that's where, if you heard the technical term in fiqh, the مُجْتَهِد is a scholar who has reached a level of اجتهاد who is able to extract directly from the Qur'an and hadith like Imam Shafi
[SPEAKER_00] 'i, Imam Abu Bakr. Imam Abu Hanifa, Imam Ahmad al-Khambar, Imam Malik, and others. So that's called a مُجْتَهِد. But that comes from the same root because they've worked so hard to attain the knowledge that they're able to basically expend all their efforts to extract rules directly from the Qur'an and Sunnah. But the literal meaning of مُجْتَهِد is hardworking. That's why they say مُجْتَهِد is hardworking, right? Yeah, exactly. Okay. So مُجْتَهِد means hardworking. Okay. It comes from the same word as جُهْد and جِهَاد, right? So again, it's from the same concept of striving and putting in effort. Okay. Now, let's see. رضا عبد الرحيم طالب مُجْتَهِد Take me through the four steps. Same gender. Good. They're both male. Singular. Good. They're both singular.
[SPEAKER_00] Good. They're both indefinite. And the same ending. Very good. They both have ضم at the end. Very good. So how would you translate it? Good. Although very is not there, but yeah. Good. All right. Continue. رثمان محمود محمود طالب كسلانو Okay. طالب كسلانو كسلان means lazy. طالب كسلانو طالب كسلانو All right. كسلانو Okay. This is this word. Okay. We have to go through this next time because time is up. But just know that كسلانو is an exception. This is one of the words that cannot have It cannot have تنوين.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay. So even though technically it's supposed to be كسلانون But just because of its nature of how it is, it cannot accept تنوين. Right? It can only have one ضم. Otherwise, it should be كسلانون. But this is still موصوف and صفة. طالب كسلانو is موصوف صفة. But we'll go into more details on this in the next lesson, إن شاء الله تعالى. Okay. Are these exceptions? Yeah. So now I think it's time to... Finally, we've grown up enough. I'm going to actually explain the exception now. All right. For the next lesson, إن شاء الله. Right? We think we're ready for it, right? Yes. Okay. So we'll explain the exception, why the exception is there. And hopefully that'll explain a lot of things, إن شاء الله. Okay? All right. Very quickly read the four lines. Quickly. So sorry. طالب كسلانو means a lazy student. Right? They're both the same. They're both male. They're both singular. They're both...
[SPEAKER_00] They're both... Next. And they're both... And they're in the same... Continue. Lazy student, huh? Huh? Lazy is masculine. Yeah, masculine, yeah. I mean, you can have... You can say it in feminine. كسلا means in a female word version. Continue. No, that's different. This word is different. It's just an exceptional word. Who are you? أنا طالب. I'm a student. أنت طالب جديد. Are you a new student? Good. This is also... What is this? طالب جديد. مصوف. مصوف and صفة. Right? So, because they fit in those four things. Hopefully we all know them by now. Continue. نعم. أنا طالب جديد. Yes, I'm a new student. Good. Mashallah. Okay, I want you to do the tamrins. Number one is Wednesday, right? Yes, you have all the way to Monday. Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So, one is... One is those who did not say anything today. And most likely I know you probably didn't do the homework. Otherwise, you would have been bursting to give some answers, right? So, whoever didn't do it, please, I want to hear your examples, inshallah, on Monday. I want everybody to look in the Qur'an and really try to decipher where are the مصوف and صفة. Okay? That's their homework. Then, number one, right? It just says, اقرأ وقت to read and write. But what I want you to do is, I want you to just underline. The مصوف and صفة here, right? Number one. And I want you to do, to think, you don't have to write it down because it will take too long. But think to yourself, go through the four steps for each one, right? Okay, they're both the same in this, but they're both the same in this. Go through it in your mind, right? Because, again, I want to build this automatic process within you that as soon as you see two similar words, you're going to go through it in your mind and at some point, it will literally be like second nature. You don't even have to think about all these things. So, that's your homework. Just that one, Tamreen. Tamreen.
[SPEAKER_00] I could give you number two, but I think that should be enough for now. Number one, inshallah. So, just underline? Yeah. Actually, do number two, too. Okay? Basically, fill in the blanks with a صفة that is مناسب, that is befitting, right? خديجة طالبة If it's from some of this class, I'll say جميلة, right? Right? So, but just put in any صفة. Any adjective that matches, but you have to make sure it fits those four rules, right? Otherwise, it's not a صفة. Okay? So, that's number two. And then the rest, inshallah. Well, number three. Okay, I'm not going to. Just do number three, too. Right? You have all the way until Monday. Number three is the same thing. It's just the opposite. Instead of filling in the صفة, you have to fill in the موصوف. Right? So, it's the same thing. Okay? So, one, two, and three. All right. Inshallah. We want to start moving faster now. Inshallah, we have a lot to cover. We want to learn Arabic. Right? Within these
[SPEAKER_00] two or three years. So, we have to cover more ground, inshallah. سبحان الله و بحمده و سبحانك اللهم و بحمدك. إن شاء الله لا إله إلا أنت نستغفر و أنت أبوذي.